A Finding Aid to the Otto and Vivika Heino Papers, 1895-2002, bulk 1940s-2000, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Otto and Vivika Heino papers
1895-2000
bulk 1940s-2000
Archives of American Art
Heino, Otto, 1915-2009
Heino, Vivika, 1910-1995
AAA.heinotto
Archival Resource Key
2.3 Linear feet
The papers of ceramicists and educators Otto and Vivika Heino measure 2.3 linear feet and date from 1895 to 2002, with the bulk of the records dating from the 1940s to 2000. The material documents the lives and careers of Otto and Vivika Heino through a mix of personal and professional papers, printed material, a video recording of a documentary, and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records or audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Scope and Contents
The papers of ceramicists and educators Otto and Vivika Heino measure 2.3 linear feet and date from 1895 to 2002, with the bulk of the records dating from the 1940s to 2000. The material documents the lives and careers of Otto and Vivika Heino through a mix of personal and professional papers, printed material, a video recording of a documentary, and photographs.
Personal and professional papers consist of correspondence, personal business records, exhibition papers, scant financial records, resumes, writings, and a video recording of a documentary titled "You Are the Miracle: Exploring the Creative Process."
Printed material includes newspaper and magazine clippings, mailings and advertisements from The Pottery, announcements, advertisements, and some catalogs from Heino exhibitions, studio events, and sales. Printed material can also be found in two scrapbooks.
Photographs depict Otto and Vivika working and teaching in their studios, exhibitions, professional events, family and friends and friendly gatherings, marionette shows, pets, and properties.
Biographical / Historical
Vivika and Otto Heino were ceramicists and educators active primarily in California, New Hampshire, and Rhode Island.
Vivika Heino (1910-1995) was born Vivika Place in Caledonia, New York. She attended Rochester Normal School and took a sculpture class, a drawing class at the Memorial Art Gallery, and a design class at the University of Rochester Extension. She then attended Colorado College of Education where she received her BA and became involved with puppeteering. By 1934 she had moved to California, where she apprenticed with a bookbinder, Mr. Bitteroff, making candlesticks, tin trays, and other small crafts. She also apprenticed with wood carver Charlie Sayers in Carmel, carving picture frames and furniture for about seven months, before learning weaving at Swedish Applied Arts in San Francisco.
While at Swedish Applied Arts, Place worked and became friends with Harry Dixon, Armank Harranian, Margaret Gravandar, and Bill Saroyan. She also found time to work as a puppeteer with Ralph Chesse and the Works Progress Administration. She also began studying pottery with Manuel Eugene Jalanivich at California University of Fine Arts, and subsequently focused primarily on pottery for the rest of her career.
Place began working with Glen Lukens at the University of Southern California in 1940. Lukens and Dr. Morley, director of the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, recommended her for a scholarship at New York State College of Ceramics in Alfred, New York, from which she graduated in 1944. She subsequently took a teaching position at the League of New Hampshire Arts and Crafts where she met Otto Heino.
One of twelve siblings, Otto Heino (1915-2009) was born in East Hampton, Connecticut, to a market gardening family of Finnish descent. The family moved to New Hampshire to sell milk when Otto was 12, and around that time he began apprenticing as a wood turner for Louie Harr. Heino was then drafted into the military and became a gunner in the United States Air Force. Between flying twenty-five missions in Europe, Heino took classes in England, made jewelry, did wood working, traveled to museums, and met individual potters and silversmiths. After visiting Leach's Pottery in Cornwall, and investigating pottery in other parts of Europe, Otto was determined to study pottery on the GI Bill on his return to the United States.
Otto and Vivika met while Otto was a student at the League of New Hampshire Arts and Crafts, where Vivian was an instructor. They married in 1950 and went on to establish their reputations as artists and educators by widely exhibiting their work, leading workshops, conducting studio open houses, consulting on film productions, and teaching at various schools and institutions. They both taught at the University of Southern California, the Chouinard Art Institute, and Rhode Island School of Design; Vivika also taught at the Sheridan School of Design in Ontario, Canada, and New England College in Henniker, New Hampshire. They operated The Potter, a studio and retail store in Ojai, California, from 1973 to 1995.
The work of Otto and Vivika Heino can be found in the collections of many museums, including the Smithsonian's Cooper-Hewitt National Design Museum, the Long Beach Museum of Art, the Los Angeles County Museum of Art, and the Ariana Museum, in Geneva, Switzerland.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated in 2003 and 2004 by Otto Heino as part of the Nanette L. Laitman Documentation Project for Craft and Decorative Arts in America.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged as three series.
Series 1: Personal and Professional Papers, 1942-2000 (Box 1; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 2: Printed Material, 1933-2000 (Box 1, 3; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 3: Photographs, 1895-2000, bulk 1940s-1990s (Box 1-3; 0.8 linear feet)
Scrapbooks; Video recordings; Ceramicists -- California; Pottery craft; Ceramicists -- New Hampshire; Ceramicists -- Rhode Island; Educators -- California; Educators -- Rhode Island -- Providence; Educators -- New Hampshire; Women potters; Women art teachers; Women artists; Women ceramicists; Women educators; Nanette L. Laitman Documentation Project for Craft and Decorative Arts in America
- Personal and Professional Papers, 1942-2000; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.8 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes personal papers such as plans, correspondence, and other materials related to the Heino's house; correspondence with friends and family; and awards and certificates received by the two artists. Professional papers consist of correspondence, price lists, loan forms, invoices, shipping documents, and acquisition information. Also found are some printed material and photographs that document the Heino's exhibitions and their relationships with museums, galleries, and professional organizations; scattered writings by and about the pair, including formulas, and a video recording of a documentary about them.
  - American Craftsmen's Council, 1957-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificates, 1973, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chouinard Art Institute, Teacher's Inservice Training in Glazes, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Personal, 1955-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Professional, 1958-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Exhibitions, 1964-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Glazes, Original Copies, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - House on McAndrew, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Invoices, Sets, 1987-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Invoices and Receipts, 1962-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - League of New Hampshire Arts and Crafts, Membership Handbook, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Museums and Galleries, Archival Resource Key
    - Archives of American Art, 1973, 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Charles A. Wustum Museum, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - The Clay Pigeon Gallery, 1994-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - The Clay Place, 1991-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Concord Arts and Crafts, 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Contemporary Crafts Gallery, 1991-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Crafts Alliance Gallery, 1993-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - The Craftsman's Gallery, 1991-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Deboer Gallery, 1991-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - The Gallery, Indiana, 1990-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Human Arts, 1991-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Long Beach Museum of Art, 1961, 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Mingei International Museum of World Folk Art, 1993-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Pewabic Pottery, 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Pinch Pottery, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Potters Wheel Gallery, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - San Francisco Craft and Folk Art Museum, 1992-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Ventura Museum, 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Viewpoint Gallery, 1990-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Otto's File, 1942-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Quotations and Excerpts, circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Resumes, 1994-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Stationery and Business Material, 1950s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Southern California Designer-Craftsmen, Ethics and By-Laws, 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - "Vivika and Otto, A Union of "Art and Heart"", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Workshops, 1981, 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Writings, Notes, Papers, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - "You are the Miracle: Exploring the Power of the Creative Process", 1994; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Printed Material, 1933-2002; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Box 1, 3
  Found here are articles and newspaper clippings on the two artists, including articles documenting Vivika's various Marionette groups; announcements from exhibitions, sales, workshops, and open houses; and several exhibition catalogs. Two scrapbooks contain clippings related to marionettes, other artists and art movements, and travel, as well as Vivika's MA commencement schedule, and some photographs and correspondence. This series also contains mailings and advertisements from The Pottery, a studio and retail store which Otto and Vivika operated in California.
  - Articles and Newspaper Clippings, 1950s-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Articles and Newspaper Clippings, Marionettes, Vivika; Sketches, 1933-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Auctions and Sales, 1960s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1950s-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Group Shows, 1955-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, Group Shows, 1965-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Newsletters and Publicity, 1959-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Other Artists Materials, circa 1950-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Potters Directories, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - The Pottery, Advertisements and Artist Cards, 1955-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Studio Open House and Workshops, 1955-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Scrapbook, Commencement Schedule, Travel Clippings, Marionette, 1932-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook, Other Artists, Correspondence, Photograph, 1940s-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook Fragments, 1940-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Miscellaneous, 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Photographs, 1895-2000, bulk 1940s-1990s; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.8 Linear feet Box 1-3
  Images include photographs and some slides that depict the artists in their studios, with their art, at professional events and friendly gatherings, and teaching. Images of Vivika include baby portraits, pictures from marionette shows, and pictures of her family. Images of Otto include snapshots from his time in the military in Europe, and photos of his family. Also included are some images of artwork and The Pottery, and images of the couple's pets, properties, and exhibitions.
  - Artists, Otto and Vivika Heino, circa 1950-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Artists, Otto Heino, 1940s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Artists, Vivika Place Heino, 1910-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Artwork, 1940s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Artwork, Photograph Album, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Exhibitions, 1953-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Events and Gatherings, circa 1940-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Family, 1895-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Family, Photograph Album, circa 1895-1915; Archival Resource Key (Box 3)
  - Marionettes, 1940s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Pets and Places, 1949-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mixed Slides, Artwork, Personal, Studio, 1960s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)